Finding Aid for Charles William Carpenter Papers, 1909-1970
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles William Carpenter Papers 1909-1970
Carpenter, Charles William,1886-1971.
1 linear ft. and 2 oversize folders
85877 Aa 2; UAm; UAl
Graduate of Tuskegee Institute in 1909, later pastor of the Second Baptist Church of Ann Arbor, Michigan. Correspondence, including letters from Mr. and Mrs. Booker T. Washington, 1909-1915; and miscellaneous sermons, prayers, church bulletins, reports of the Second Baptist Church and other materials concerning his work with the Ann Arbor Human Relations Commission, the Citizens Advisory Committee for a Workable Program, and the Ann Arbor Bus Committee.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Rev. Carpenter (donor no. 4333 ) and came to the library in different accessions, mainly in 1972.
The collection is open to research.
Charles W. Carpenter was born on May 1, 1886 in Stanford, Kentucky, but later moved to Indianapolis where he attended night school. He graduated from Tuskegee Institute in 1909, then attended the Payne Theological Seminary at Wilberforce University. In 1916, he graduated from the Garrett Biblical Institute in Evanston, Illinois. Carpenter had previously entered the ministry in Detroit in 1912, then served as pastors of churches in various communities in Indiana, Minnesota, Illinois, and Ontario. He became pastor of Second Baptist Church in Ann Arbor in 1929, and served there until his retirement in 1966. He died in 1971.
The Carpenter collection includes correspondence, files relating to his community interests and involvements, sermons and prayers, files detailing his services with Second Baptist Church, and photographs.
Subjects:
African Americans--Michigan.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Clergy--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Second Baptist Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Tuskegee Institute.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
African Americans--Spiritual life.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Churches.; Carpenter, Charles William, 1886-1971.; Churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Interiors.; Second Baptist Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Contributors:
Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915.; Washington, Margaret James Murray, 1861-1925.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - 1909-1950 (Box 1)
  - 1951-1960 (Box 1)
  - 1961-1966 (Box 1)
- Community Interests
  - Ann Arbor Human Relations Commission, 1963-1965 (Box 1)
  - Citizens Advisory Committee for Workable Program, 1963-1970 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor "Fair Housing" ordinance, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Bus Committee, 1956 (Box 1)
- Sermons and prayers
  - Sermons, undated and 1929-1966, 11 folders (Box 1)
  - Christmas sermons (Box 1)
  - Radio sermons, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Sermons by guest speakers (Box 1)
  - Prayers (Box 1)
- Pastoral activities
  - Sessions minutes of the Ontario Annual Conference of the African Methodist Episcopal Church, 1925-1926 (Box 1)
  - National Baptist Convention, 1957-1965 (Box 1)
  - Financial reports of the Ann Arbor Second Baptist Church, 1942-1961 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous programs of services, Ann Arbor Second Baptist Church (Box 1)
  - Harvest Home Celebration, Ann Arbor Second Baptist Church (Box 1)
  - Constitution and by-laws, Ann Arbor Second Baptist Church (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Sunday School material (Box 1)
  - Report to the General Baptist State Convention on the depression with particular reference to the Negro, August 1933 (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Church bulletins (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous printed materials (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Photos of Second Baptist Church and church functions; also photos of Carpenter at other ceremonies (Box 1)
    (see also oversize folders UAm and UAl)